Guide to the Aisling Irish Community Center Oral History Collection AIA.035
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Aisling Irish Community Center Oral History Collection
2006
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Aisling Irish Community Center
AIA.035
0.5 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
This collection of oral histories and the resulting publication, "When Mem'ry Brings Us Back Again" describe life for newly arrived immigrants in New York City in the 1950s and 1960s. The impetus for the project was a creative writing class run at the Aisling irish Community Center.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into one alphabetical series
Historical/Biographical Note
The Aisling Irish Community Center is located in Yonkers, New York. Established in 1996, the Center serves to assist Irish immigrants moving to the United States, much like the Emerald Isle Immigration Center in Woodside, Queens. The Aisling Center also provides services for the elderly Irish and Irish-American community in Yonkers and Woodlawn. This project of recording memories evolved from a program at the Center for Seniors called "Young at Heart." Staff member Frances Browner initiated a creative writing class which focused on different themes and memories of the participants. From the exercise the idea of recording the stories and creating the narrative was formed. The result is the book While Mem'ry Brings us Back Again.
The participants tell of coming to America, the different ships they took, their impressions of New York - the weather, the tall buildings, navigating the subway, electricity and indoor plumbing - their first jobs, their friendships and social activities, and their homesickness. For many, leaving to come to America was also the first time they had ever been out of their hometown. Some came voluntarily; others were chosen or sent by a family member.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Missing Title
Ireland House Oral History Colletion AIA 030
Jane Conlon Muller Oral History Collection AIA 012
Miriam Nyhan Oral History Collection AIA 036
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of interviews conducted with Irish immigrants by Frances Browner in 2006 for the book "When Mem'ry Brings Us Back Again." A copy of the book is included with the collection. Interviews are recorded on compact disk, also included in the collection. Oftentimes, the recordings were made in public places such as restaurants or bars, and the clarity has been compromised because of the background noise. The interviews were transcribed into narratives which comprise the book.
Interviewees describe their trips to America, usually by ship; sometimes by airplane. First jobs, for the women oftentimes at Shrafts, a restaurant chain in Manhattan, the telephone company, with mass transit, for B. Dalton, a department store, as a professional musician and employed by wealthy families as domestic workers are discussed as are reminisces of social activities and outings.
When available, duration of interviews is recorded and is included in the container list.
Provenance
Transcripts and copies of original audio recordings along with a copy of the resulting publication "When Mem'ry Brings Us Back Again" were donated to the Archives of Irish America in 2006.
Custodial History
The archived website was migrated from the California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service to the Internet Archive's Archive-It Service in November 2015. The link to California Digital Library was removed in October 2017.
Oral histories (literary works); CD-ROMs.; Immigrants -- United States.; Oral history.; Irish Americans -- New York (N.Y.); Irish Americans -- Social life and customs.
- Printed Materials and Research, 2006
  - While Mem'ry Brings us Back Again: A Collection of Memoirs, 2006 (Box 1, Cd data_value_missing_f02aa5db1c3af91b517f9261b832a12f)
  - Miscellaneous Extracts compiled for "While Mem'ry Brings us Back Again" or Fran Brownwer's Creative Writing Class, 2006 (Box 1, Cd data_value_missing_196ee64c8e66c305d0deb81e73676c28)
  - Miscellaneous Extracts compiled for While Mem'ry Brings us Back Again or Fran Brownwer's Creative Writing Class on CD, 2006 (Box 2, Cd 1)
  - Aisling Project Photos by Nuala Purcell CD-1. Contains images of interviewees in book and some events, 2006 (Box 2, Cd 2)
  - Aisling Project Photos by Nuala Purcell CD-2 (2 copies) Contains images of Rose McGurk, Oliver O'Donnell and Jimmy Clarke, 2006 (Box 2, Cd 03, 03.1)
  - Aisling Project Photos: Carme Purcell, undated (Box 2, Cd 4)
  - Aisling Project Photos: Gaelic Park Crowd Shots, Oct 1, 2006 (Box 2, Cd 5)
- Interviews, 2006
  - Burke, Bill: President: Country Bank, New York (file in unknown MSV format), undated (Box 2, Cd 6)
  - Butler, Chris: County Offaly - New York I, undated (Box 2, Cd 7)
  - Butler, Chris: County Offaly - New York II, undated (Box 2, Cd 8)
  - Chambers, Jimmy and Anne I, undated (Box 2, Cd 9)
  - Chambers, Jimmy and Anne II (Box 2, Cd 10)
  - Clarke, Jimmy (b. 1906) Arrived New York 1927, County Galway; duration 23:55, Feb 2006 (Box 2, Cd 11)
  - Connaughton, Terry; duration 36:44, undated (Box 2, Cd 12)
  - Cregan, Jerry and Marian I, undated (Box 2, Cd 40)
  - Cregan, Jerry and Marian II, undated (Box 2, Cd 41)
  - Cremin, Mike, County Kerry - New York; duration 51:43, undated (Box 2, Cassette 13)
  - Crowe, Therese, Tipperary - New York; duration 46:01, undated (Cd 2, Cd 14)
  - Cunningham, Joe; duration 1:13:38, undated (Box 2, Cd 15)
  - Cunningham, Rose; duration 12:12, WAV file, undated (Box 2, Cassette 16)
  - Cunningham, Rose; duration 12:12, MPEG4 file (Box 2, Cd 17)
  - Delaney, Agnes I, undated (Box 2, Cd 18)
  - Delaney, Agnes II (Box 2, Cd 19)
  - Doyle, Julia: County Kilkenny (1951) New York; duration 50:01, undated (Box 2, Cd 20)
  - Fleming, Sean I, undated (Box 2, Cd 21)
  - Fleming, Sean II, undated (Box 2, Cd 22)
  - Fleming, Sean III, undated (Box 2, Cd 23)
  - Glendon, Bridget: Donegal - New York, undated (Box 2, Cd 24)
  - McCarrick, Thomas: County Sligo - New York; duration 6:13, undated (Box 2, Cd 25)
  - McGurk, Rose: Derry, Arrived 1928 to New York I, undated (Box 2, Cd 26)
  - McGurk, Rose: Derry, Arrived 1928 to New York II, undated (Box 2, Cd 27)
  - McNamara, Theresa: Leitrim - New York; duration 53:16, undated (Box 2, Cd 28)
  - Mulcahey, Denis I, undated (Box 2, Cd 42)
  - Mulcahey, Denis II, undated (Box 2, Cd 43)
  - Murray, Patrick and Phil I; duration 58:65 (MP3 file converted to WAV on server), undated (Box 2, Cd 29)
  - Murray, Patrick and Phil I; duration 53:30 (MP3 file converted to WAV on server), undated (Box 2, Cassette 30)
  - O'Donnell, Oliver; duration 44:16, undated (Box 2, Cd 31)
  - O'Halloran, Michael and Martin O'Malley; duration 1:05:15, undated (Box 2, Cd 32)
  - Purcell, Carmen: Belfast - New York; duration 29:12, undated (Box 2, Cd 33)
  - Young at Heart Senior Group at Aisling Irish Community Center, Yonkers, NY: Discuss the Dance Halls (CD #1), undated (Box 2, Cd 34)
  - Young at Heart Senior Group at Aisling Irish Community Center, Yonkers, NY (CD #2), Nov 2005 (Box 2, Cd 35)
  - Young at Heart Senior Group at Aisling Irish Community Center, Yonkers, NY: Discuss Coming to America (CD #3), Nov 2005 (Box 2, Cd 36)
  - Young at Heart Senior Group at Aisling Irish Community Center, Yonkers, NY: Discuss Shopping at Fordham Road (CD #4), undated (Box 2, Cd 37)
  - Young at Heart Senior Group at Aisling Irish Community Center, Yonkers, NY (CD #5), undated (Box 2, Cd 38)
  - Young at Heart: Jpegs and Word documents, no audio (Box 2, Cd 39)
- Archived Website, Mar 28, 2014-ongoing
  Scope and Content Note
  The Aisling Irish Community Center is located in Yonkers, New York. Established in 1996, the Center serves to assist Irish immigrants moving to the United States. The Aisling Center also provides services for the elderly Irish and Irish-American community in Yonkers and Woodlawn. The website contains event and classes schedules, a photo gallery, and news listings.